# KAROL CHLASTA





### **SUMMARY**

Senior technology leader, expert in driving strategic initiatives in technology and financial services. Extensive experience in business intelligence and financial reporting systems (IFRS and Solvency II), data, DevOps as well as cyber threat & vulnerability management. Demonstrable track in project delivery and process transformation. Collaborative leader with proven skills in recruiting, mentoring, and growing teams. Currently a PhD student in Computer Science at PJAIT/SWPS University, where he works on artificial intelligence in clinical applications. 14 years of experience in different IT roles, including 8 years in leadership positions.



### **EDUCATION**

# PhD Student Computer Science | Polish-Japanese Academy of Information Technology OCTOBER 2018 – NOW

Interdisciplinary PhD studies in the area of ICT & Psychology, run jointly by Polish-Japanese Academy of Information Technology and SWPS University of Social Sciences and Humanities. Courses and projects in Big Data & Machine Learning, Biocybernetics, Natural Language Processing. Developed new algorithm for speech classification: 3 articles published, 2 more submitted.

### Postgraduate Business Analytics | Warsaw University of Technology OCTOBER 2014 – JUNE 2015

Postgraduate Diploma in Business Analytics from the Institute of Computer Science, Faculty of Electronics and Information Technology (part-time). Thesis: Implementation of sentiment analysis model for Twitter data in Polish language (with distinction).

### **MSc Economic Computer Science | Cracow University of Economics**

OCTOBER 2003 - JANUARY 2008

Graduated with MSc in Information Technology and Econometrics – Economic Computer Science from the Department of Management (full-time). Member of IT Student Club (2004-07), ISACA Poland (2005-07) and Polish Linux User Group (2003-now). Academic exchanges to France (ESDES Ecole Supérieure de Commerce & Management – 1 semester), Finland (Centria-ammattikorkeakoulu – 1 semester), and the UK (University of the West of Scotland – 1 year).



### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

### Kozminski University, Warsaw, Poland

#### **Cloud Infrastructure and Business IT Tools, Scrum Foundations**

FEBRUARY 2021 - NOW

45 hours with BSc students of management and artificial intelligence programme (2 different groups).

# University of Information Technology and Management, Olsztyn, Poland Business Intelligence Systems, Modern Database Systems, Multimedia Technologies OCTOBER 2020 – NOW

Designed, developed, and delivered three courses for the engineering students in:

- computer science (2<sup>nd</sup> year, 45 hours of lectures and laboratories in Multimedia Technologies in the Internet Environment),
- computer science (3<sup>rd</sup> year, 18 hours of lectures and laboratories in Business Intelligence Systems on the advanced level)
- industrial management (2<sup>nd</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> year, 20 hours of lectures in Business Intelligence Systems, and in Modern Database Systems).

# Polish-Japanese Academy of Information Technology, Warsaw, Poland Advanced Multimedia Techniques

OCTOBER 2019 - FERBUARY 2021

30 hours with MSc students of computer science and new media arts (3 different groups) in 2020, 5 hours in 2021.



### **ACADEMIC COLLABORATION**

## Member of Eye Tracking Research Center | SWPS University, Warsaw, Poland (website) DECEMBER 2018 – NOW

Collaborating with prof. Izabela Krejtz and Krzysztof Krejtz in the fields of psychology, eye-tracking, and human-computer interaction.

### IT Expert | Mobility Research Group, SWPS University, Warsaw, Poland (website)

FEBRUARY 2020 - NOW

Collaborating with prof. Izabela Grabowska and her team in the field of social informatics (Digital Traces of Migrants).

### Reviewer of Yearbook of the Poznań LM | Adam Mickiewicz University, Poznań, Poland (website) NOVEMBER 2020 – JANUARY 2021

Yearbook of the Poznań Linguistic Meeting (ISSN: 2449-7525) carries selected papers based on presentations at the Poznań Linguistic Meeting, a leading European linguistics conference.



### **PUBLICATIONS**

• Le, D., Tran, T., **Chlasta, K**., Krejtz, K., Fjeld, M., Kunz, A. (2021). VXSlate: Combining Head Movement and Mobile Touch for Large Virtual Display Interaction. IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces, ISBN 978-0-7381-1367-8.

https://doi.org/10.1109/VRW52623.2021.00146 (video)

- Chlasta, K., Wołk, K. (2020). Towards computer-based automated screening of dementia through spontaneous speech. Frontiers in Psychology Human Media Interaction, Volume 11, 4091.
   <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.623237">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.623237</a>
- Chlasta, K., Wołk, K., & Krejtz, I. (2019). Automated speech-based screening of depression using deep convolutional neural networks. Procedia Computer Science, Volume 164, 2019, 618-628, ISSN 1877-0509. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procs.2019.12.228



#### **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- Data Science Summit 2020, Warsaw, Poland. Together with Paweł Holas (University of Warsaw, Faculty of Psychology) presented: "Detecting depression and dementia in speech with machine learning" (<u>link</u>).
- International Conference on Telemedicine & eHealth, Warsaw, Poland, organized by Polish Telemedicine and eHealth Society (September 18th, 2020). Presentation title: "Automation of depression screening by applying machine learning to gaze pattern analysis" (link). Received award for the best presentation (link).
- International Conference on Telemedicine & eHealth, Warsaw, Poland, organized by Polish Telemedicine and eHealth Society (November 22nd-23rd, 2019). Presentation title: "Application of machine learning algorithms to automate depression screening" (link).
- HCist 2019 International Conference on Health and Social Care Information Systems and Technologies, an Association for Information Systems affiliated conference, Sousse, Tunisia (October 16-18th, 2019). Presented "Automated speech-based screening of depression using deep convolutional neural networks".
- Co-organizer and speaker at dbConf, Hucisko-Zawiercie, Poland (October 28th, 2015). Together with Antoni Sobkowicz (Polish National Information Processing Institute) presented: "Sentiment Analysis Our approach and use cases" (video).
- Speaker at dbConf, Szczyrk, Poland (October 25th, 2014). Presentation title: "High-performance Business Intelligence solution based on IBM Cognos and ParAccel Analytic Database" (video).

• Speaker at the International Conference for Young Researchers, University of Economics, Kishinev, Moldova (April 21st-22nd, 2005). Presented two topics: "Wireless Internet Adoption in Poland in 2005", and "Advantages and Disadvantages of Software Patents".



### **KEY SKILLS & AWARDS**

- 19+ professional certificates: Huawei AI + Security (2 exams),
   MicroStrategy (4 exams + project), IBM Cognos (4 exams), EMC Captiva (3 exams), IBM DB2 (2 exams), hands-on experience with several aspects of IT
- Strong technical acumen with ability to quickly learn and contribute to technical discussions
- Proven people and project leadership, experience in setting up new teams, hiring, retaining talented engineers
- Well organized, analytical approach, communicative (incl. Polish, English, French)

- 2017 Aviva Global CIO Award Global Winner in Outstanding Leadership Category
- Outstanding Academic
   Achievement Award for
   Students from Polish Minister of
   Higher Education (2005)



### **ORGANIZATIONS & ACTIVITIES**

- BCS Professional member (MBCS), Association for Computing Machinery, IEEE Computer Society
- Computer Science incl. Programming, Data Engineering, HCI, Linux, Cognitive Sciences, Photography, Globetrotting, Sports: Skiing, Running (Warsaw Marathon in 4:25, Yorkshire in 4:13, Tel-Aviv Marathon in 4:12, Krynica Marathon, the most difficult road run in Poland in 4:26, Northern Marathon, Hel-Władysławowo in 4:07)



### **ADDITIONAL PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

# Systems Development & Vulnerability Manager | Aviva OCTOBER 2016 – NOW (WARSAW)

- As a senior manager (IT-E) in AGC Corporate Functions CIO directly responsible for a mix of up to 11 employees and consultants (based in Warsaw, London and Norwich), led several projects incl. final stages of global Solvency II deployment, and now leading BAU change (engagement/PM, application development, DevOps, testing) for the Aviva's IFRS and Solvency II financial reporting systems. Hands-on experience with:
  - o SAP BusinessObjects Financial Consolidation (BFC),
  - o SAP Disclosure Management (DM),
  - o SAP Financial Information Management (FIM),
  - o SAP BusinessObjects Business Intelligence (BI),
  - o AWS Cloud, Bitbucket, Jenkins, Puppet, Packer, Terraform, Groovy and others.
- Additional responsibility, as the Vulnerability Manager to re-shape and manage the Vulnerability Management Programme across AGC Corporate Functions CIO. This resulted in the closure of a long running (7 years) global VM audit issue. Before 2019 setup of the new Corporate Functions IT department in Warsaw, growing the team up to 34+ FTEs with operations and resource management for Finance, Actuarial, Risk & Legal teams.

### **Development Manager | Brown Brothers Harriman**

JANUARY 2015 – SEPTEMBER 2016 (KRAKOW)

• BBH Technology (Applications Development – Digital Client Experience Systems), global head of BI development function.

### Sr Analyst, Team Leader and Manager | Royal Bank of Scotland

FEBRUARY 2011 – DECEMBER 2014 (WARSAW/AMSTERDAM)

• Vice President at RBS Group (Business Intelligence & Decision Support).

# Business Intelligence Consultant, Architect | MicroStrategy/Tesco Bank NOVEMBER 2009 – JANUARY 2011 (EDINBURGH/GLASGOW)

• As a MicroStrategy On-Site Lead deployed MicroStrategy 9 enterprise BI platform for the General Insurance business of a recently established Tesco Bank.

### Jr System Administrator, IT Application Support Specialist | IBM

JULY 2007 - OCTOBER 2009 (KRAKOW)

• At Global Cost Management Tools Team (IBM Global Services – U.S. based Business Process Delivery), and Cracow IT Team (IBM Global Services – Business Process Delivery).

### Software Developer | Hewlett-Packard

AUGUST 2006 – NOVEMBER 2006 (WARSAW)

• Apprentice software developer in HP Technology Solutions Group - C&I Application Services.